A Guide to the Carter Family Papers, 1718-1833
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carter Family Papers, 1718-1833
Library of Virginia
25840
138 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by the James Monroe Memorial Foundation, Fredericksburg, Virginia, through George H. S. King, 1301 Prince Edward Street, Fredericksburg, Virginia, 5 August 1963.
Biographical Information
Robert "King" Carter (1663-1732) was one of the largest land holders in Virginia and one of its most prominent leaders. King Carter lived at Coromoton in Lancaster County, Virginia. He and his first wife Judith Armistead Carter (1665-1699) had five children. King Carter and his second wife Betty Landon Willis Carter (1683/4-1719) had ten children. Charles Carter of Cleve (1707-1764), in King George County, Virginia, was the fifth child of King Carter and Betty Carter. His son was Charles Carter of Ludow (1732-1796). Charles Carter of Shirley (1732-1806), in Charles City County, Virginia, was the son of John Carter (1689-1742), first son of King Carter and Judith Carter. Carter of Shirley married Mary Walker Carter (ca. 1736-1770), daughter of Charles Carter of Cleve. Robert Carter of Nomini (1728-1804), in Richmond County, Virginia, was the son of Robert Carter (1704-1732), the oldest son of King Carter and his second wife Betty. St. Leger Landon Carter (1785-1850) was the son of Landon Carter of Cleve (1751-1811), son of Charles Carter of Cleve. Robert Wormeley Carter (1733-1797) was the son of Landon Carter of Sabine Hall (1710-1778), the seventh child of King Carter and Betty Carter. Robert Wormeley Carter's son was George Carter (d. 1802). Henry Rose Carter (1810-1881) was the son of Hill Carter of Mine Run in Amherst County, Virginia, who was the son of Edward Carter (ca. 1733-1792) of Albemarle County, Virginia. Edward Carter was the son of John Carter, King Carter's oldest child by his first wife Judith.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1718-1833, of the Carter family of Lancaster and King George Counties, Virginia, consisting of accounts, bills of lading, epitaphs, invoices, letters, and wills. Accounts and invoices are for bedding, dry-goods, wigs, clothing, and a telescope purchased by members of the Carter family, also includes account of tobacco sold by Robert Carter, and accounts for medical services rendered by Dr. John Tennant and a Dr. Hall. Bills of lading record tobacco shipments from King George County to England by Charles Carter (1707-1764). Correspondence topics include business and agricultural matters such as tobacco, seeds, sheep, and copper supplies; political subjects such as the appointment of Robert Dinwiddie (1692-1770) as Governor of Virginia, Great Britain's colonial policy, the Stamp Act, the Revolution, and early United States politics; and social and family news, including Robert Carter (1663-1732) being informed his sons have arrived safely in England, the relationship between Robert Carter and his son Charles, and Robert W. Carter's concerns over his son George's gambling problems. Two letters discuss Carter family genealogy and there is also a copy of tombstone inscriptions from Christ Church in Lancaster County. Papers also include the will, 23 July 1730, of Robert "King" Carter and a roster, 29 April 1756, of the King George County militia.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Account, n.d., of Charles Carter through Thomas Main with George Adams., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, n.d., from Henry R. Carter to an unidentified recipient discussing a branch of the Carter family descended from Robert King Carter., 7 leaves, negative photostats.
- Tombstone inscriptions, n.d., of the Carter family interred at Christ Church, Lancaster County, Virginia., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 26 July 1718, from William Dawkins, London, England, to Robert King Carter, [Lancaster County, Virginia], stating that Carter's sons have arrived safely in England., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 25 June 1722, from William Dawkins, London, to Joseph Walker concerning business matters and tobacco., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 December 1728, from Edward Athawes, London, to Charles Carter, [Lancaster County], regarding copper., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 5 September 1730, from William Dawkins and Company to Charles Carter, [Lancaster County], discussing business matters, tobacco, and Charles Carter's relationship with his father, Robert King Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Invoice, December 1731, for goods shipped by William Dawkins and Company to Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Will, 23 July 1730, of Robert King Carter of Lancaster County. Will was recorded in General Court 16 October 1732., 26 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 28 November 1733, of William Dawkins and Company possibly with J. Rolleston to be shipped on the Homer, Gardiner., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 28 November 1733, of William Dawkins and Company with William Cheslyn., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 29 November 1733, of William Dawkins and Company with Ab. Pinhorn., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Account, 30 November 1733, of William Dawkins with Benjamin Gardner., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Invoice, December 1733, for goods shipped by William Dawkins and Company to Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 15 December 1733, of William Dawkins and Company with John, Thomas, and Timothy Hollis., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 February 1735, from How and Kelsick, Whitehaven, [England], to Charles Carter concerning tobacco., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Account, 28 August 1735, of Charles Carter with Dr. John Tennant for medical services rendered., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 10 March 1736, of Charles Carter with Haswell, Brookes, and Hunt., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 15 May 1736, of Charles Carter with Micajah Perry., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 November 1736, from Haswell, Brookes, and Hunt, London, to Charles Carter concerning business matters., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, 17 January 17[38/39?], from Foster Cunliff [?], Liverpool, England, to Charles Carter concerning his business dealings in tobacco, wheat, and corn., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bills of lading, 30 April 1742, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter, King George County, Virginia., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 12 July 1742, from John Lewis of Gloucester, County, Virginia, to Charles Carter regarding Lewis' matrimonial prospects wtih Miss Howell of Gloucester County., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 August 1742, from James Littlepage to Charles Carter, King George County informing Carter of the death of Mr. Randolph of Tuckahoe and other general news., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Bill of lading, 27 July 1745, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 23 September 1745, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 7 October 1745, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Bill of lading, 7 October 1745, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 25 February 1746, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 19 May 1746, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 27 June 1746, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 5 July 1746, from Nathaniel Chapman, Accokeek, [Stafford County, Virginia?], to Charles Carter concerning seeds and Carter's dispute with Mr. Meredith., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, [19?] July 1746, from G. Currell, Nomini [Westmoreland County, Virginia], to Charles Carter concerning sheep., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 1 September 1746, of tobacco sold for Robert Carter., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Bill of lading, 17 November 1746, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Bill of lading, 17 November 1746, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bills of lading, 4 May 1747, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 11 May 1747, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 24 May 1747, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 23 October 1747, for tobacco shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Bill of lading, 13 November 1747, for goods shipped by Charles Carter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 September 1751, from Lyonel Lyde, London, to Charles Carter, Jr., concerning the departure from England of Virginia's new Lieutenant Governor Robert Dinwiddie, and tobacco sales., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Account, 8 June 1754, of Charles Carter, Sr., with Nicholas Long., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, 17 April 1755, from Edmund Jennings, London, to [Charles Carter?] discussing Great Britain's attitudes towards the colonies and plans for the northern colonies., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Roster, 29 April 1756, of militia sent of King George County., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 10 June [?] 1756, of Charles Carter with James Currie, 1753-1756, for wigs., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 6 June 1757, of Charles Carter with James Currie for wigs., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 2 June 1760, of Charles Carter with James Priestman for clothing., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 8 November 1763, from Arthur [Morton or Morson?], Falmouth, Virginia, to [Charles Carter?] concerning business dealings., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 27 March 1766, from C. and O. Hanbury, London, to Charles Carter Corotoman, Lancaster County, concerning Carter's account and the stamp act., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 7 August 1778, from Henderson Inches, Boston, Massachusetts, to [Charles Carter of Shirley?] discussing the battle of Monmouth, the Continental Army, and George Washington., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 11 June 1792, .from Robert Wormeley Carter, Sabine Hall, Richmond County, Virginia, to John Minor, Fredericksburg, Virginia, concerning his son George's gambling debts., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Invoice, 25 February 1796, for goods shipped by Thomas Main, London., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Account, 1 October 1796, of Charles Carter, through Thomas Main, with Edward Nairne., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 September 1799, from John Walker, Belvoir, [Fairfax County, Virginia], to Charles Carter of Shirley, Fauquier County, Virginia, discussing a possible marriage of a friend, politics, weather, and other matters., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 26 November 1804, from Sarah Carter, King George County, to Mrs. Minor, Fredericksburg, discussing cloth and family news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Account, 2 January 1806, of Charles Carter [of Shirley?] with Dr. Hall for medical services., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 June 1833, from St. Leger L. Carter, King George County, to [William A. Moali] providing genealogical notes of the Carter family and epitaphs of Robert King Carter and family., leaves, negative photostats.